this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at SC radio net.
SC radio is brought to you by the I Triple E Computer Society.
I Triple E software magazine online at computer org slash software.
hello this is Jeremy Jung for a software engineering radio.
today I have John Doran with me.
John is the director of engineering at Forrest, a Dublin based SAS company.
that processes appointments for the hair and beauty industry.
he previously worked as a technical lead at Travelport digital.
where he supported major airlines and hotel chains with their mobile platforms.
I'll be speaking with John about the early days of their business.
the challenges they faced while scaling.
and how they were able to reshape their processes and team to overcome these challenges.
John welcome to software engineering radio.
hey Jeremy thanks so much for having me.
the first thing I'd like to discuss is the early days of Forrest.
to just give the listeners a little bit of background what what type of product is Forrest?
sure.
so Forrest is essentially it's a salon software focused in the hair and beauty industry.
and it didn't actually start off as that back in Tanana tree.
it was actually a messaging service actually built by a few students in Trinity College.
one of which was his name was Rona Percival Ron's actually our current CEO.
so that in 2003 that messaging service was supporting night lopes dentists.
various small businesses around Dublin.
and the guys were finding it really hard to get some traction in in those various different industries.
so Ronan actually went him that worked as a as a hair receptionist in in a salon.
and what he learned from that was that true using messaging.
and the platform that they were able to actually increase revenue for salons.
and actually get more money in details which was hugely powerful thing.
so from there they were able to to really focus on on that particular industry.
they built supplementary features and a product around that messaging service.
so in 2004 it became a kind of a fully alleged appointment book.
and from there then they they integrated that appointment book with the messaging service.
so by 2006 then I guess you could cook love ice forest as a full Cylon software.
so it had things like stock take financial reporting and staff rostering.
that fully based some on software system was pretty popular in ireland.
and actually by between 2006 and 2008 they became the number one in the industry in ireland.
so what that meant was you know the majority of salons in ireland were running on on the forest platform.
and that was actually an on-premise system.
so all the data would have been stored locally in the hair salon and there was no back-end.
just so I understand correctly so you say it was running on premise? mm-hmm.
it was an appointment system so is this where somebody would come into the salon.
and make an appointment and they would enter it into a local computer.
and it would be just stored there exactly?
so so what Ronan figured I'd trade his time working in the salon.
that by actually sending customers text messages to remind them that about their appointments.
really helped cut down the no-show rates.
meaning that customers did turn up their appointments when they were Jew.
and meaning that the staff members didn't have to sit around waiting for customers walking.
so as far as I guess as a company developed.
we we moved into building extra features around that core system.
which is an appointment book which manages the day-to-day rows of a hairstylist.
so we built a email and marketing retention tools around that.
okay I guess a really important point about Boris history.
is when the recession hit in Cher's innate in Ireland we moved into the UK.
so as we were kind of the number one provider in Ireland.
we felt when the recession hit that we needed to move into the UK.
but being on premise meant there was a lot of friction actually installing the system into the stands.
so in 2011 they actually took us a small seed round to build out.
I guess the declared back end went.
once that kind of cloud back-end was built to talk about a year to get it off the ground and released.
and as a company I gained traction in the UK.
they they migrated all of their on-premise customers onto the declared solution.
I guess you would say that when it was on-premise.
a lot of the engineering effort or the support effort.
was probably in keeping the software working for your customers.
and just addressing technical issues or questions and things like that.
and that was probably taking a lot of your times is that correct?
precisely the the team was quite small.
so we we had five engineers who were essentially building at the cloud back-end.
on one engineer who was maintaining that Delfy on premise application.
so what was happening was our CEO Ronan was actually the product owner at that time.
and the guys were making pretty drastic and kind of quickfire decisions.
in terms of features being added to the product.
based on you know getting a certain customer in not really needed to pay the bills.
and some of those decisions I guess made the product a bit more complex as a crew.
but it certainly was a big improvement from the on-premise solution. hmm.
so the on-premise solution you said was written in belfie is that correct? yeah.
when it was first started was it just a single developer exactly?
yeah so it was it was literally put together by some-some outsourcers. and a single developer managing it.
there was no there was no real in-house developers.
it was you know a bit of turnover there.
but when that small seed round came in.
the guys put that together the foundations of the declare base back-end.
which was a Java kind of classic interior application with WebSocket.
to update the appointment screen if anything changed on the back end.
and you would kind of consider it a majestic monolith as such.
when you started the cloud solution where you maintaining both systems simultaneously?
yeah so and for a full year the guys were building out that back-end.
and at the same time there was a one guy who was it was literally maintaining.
fixing bugs on that Delfy application.
and just to kind of give you an example.
um one of the guys who was actually working on support.
he he actually went and taught himself SQL.
and he used to tunnel into the the cylons at night to fix any database issues and.
oh well yeah so it was it was you know hardcore stuff. mm-hmm.
another big thing about not being a Clare base and I'd one of the big reasons.
we need to become player base was we you know as people move online.
and you know it's it's quite common to book you know your cinema or something else online.
but AM Ronin could see that trend coming for online bookings.
and we needed to be clear basted to build to build out that online booking system.
and just to kind of give you the an idea of the scale.
like last year we would have processed about to over 2 billion euros worth of transactions to a system.
so it's really it's really growing and you know it's huge huge scale at the moment for them.
I guess looking looking back at the past.
the guys would have built a great robust system.
getting us to about that Terezin salva mark particularly in the UK.
but if that would have been the point that the guys would have started seeing some.
you know shakiness in terms of stability.
and the speed at which at which we could deliver new new features.
you were saying the initial cloud version took about a year to create exactly? yeah.
and you had five engineers working on it after the seed round? mm-hmm.
at that time when you first started working on the the cloud version of the application.
did you have a limited rollout to kind of weed out defects.
or how did you start transferring customers over?
so there was definitely some we looked in customers to move across.
we did it I guess gradually there was a lot of reluctance for people.
people were quite scared and their data not being stored in a salon.
so it was quite hard to get those some of those customers across.
and only two weeks ago we we actually officially stopped supporting that.
and final two customers have finished up.
so you know it took us a good seven years to finish that transition.
okay so it was a very gradual transition.
where you actually what did you ask customers whether they wanted to move or how did you?
oh yeah it was a huge huge sales and team effort to get people across the line.
but I would say the majority of people I would have churned.
or or would have moved across the the more forward-thinking people.
I you know they would have been getting new features and a better service right?
so it's kind of more of a marketing push from your side to say.
hey if you move over to our cloud solution you'll get all these additional capabilities.
but it was ultimately up to them to decide whether they wanted to move.
yeah so um know some companies they they kind of build a product with a different name. and they try and sell us both.
Forrest's we actually kept the UI very similar.
so it wasn't very intrusive to the users.
it was just kind of seen as an upgrade with um I guess less friction.
right right.
I want to talk a little bit about the early days.
where you you said you spent about a year to build the MVP.
at that point let's say after that year had passed.
were you still able to iterate quickly in terms of features.
or were you having any problems with performance or downtime at that point?
so in 2012 when the cloud-based product launch ticket in the UK.
once we hit about tears and customers we started to see creaking issues in the backend.
lots of JVM garbage collection problems lots of a database contention and lots of outages.
so we we got to a point where we were trying hardware at the problem to make things a little bit faster.
some other problems were we kind of relied a lot on a single person to do a lot of the deployments.
so it wasn't really a it wasn't really a team effort to ship things.
it was more so developer finishes code in the machine push it off.
maybe at the end of the month we lead ship.
I guess the big problem was the the stability.
so essentially what what happened was in terms of the architecture.
we were introducing caches at various levels to try and cope with performance.
so a layer of caching on the client-side was introduced.
memcache key was introduced level level to hibernate caching.
always just you know really focusing on fixing the immediate problem.
without looking at kind of the bigger picture.
once I said I mentioned that tears and silence as a marker.
I guess once we hit like twelve hundred.
the guys had to introduce the idea of silos.
which was like essentially one tears and customers are going to be linked to a specific URL.
and that URL will host the API return back the data they need.
and then the other silo which would serve as theater.
you know two hundred growing to say it hasn't businesses.
so essentially if you think about it you've got I guess a big point of failure.
if if that if that server goes down there's no load balancing bit between between servers.
and those two servers are their biggest size possible.
so I guess a big red herring was the cost I guess implications of that.
you know it was the largest instance type on Amazon or des on DC.
to level the entire system was on a single instance for each silo?
yeah so if you imagine when you when you log in.
you'll get returned a URL for a particular silo.
so what would happen then would be X businesses go to that silo.
and X Y businesses go to the other side.
and what that did was basically low balanced the the businesses at a kind of a database level.
you were mentioning how you had like different caching layers for example.
memcache D and things like that yeah but those were all being run on the same instance is that correct?
I am they would have been hosted by Amazon.
okay so those would have been Amazon's hosted services so yeah. yeah.
okay it's kind of like when you build a 10 BP or you build that initial stage your products.
kind of you're focusing on building features.
you're focusing on getting bombs on seats on you.
it was that point that well we got 1,200 to the tears and Cylons that where we filled that pain.
that's geylang pain. mm-hmm.
so in a way like you said you were doing multi-tenancy.
but it was kind of split per thousand customers?
yeah exactly so if you imagine if a failure happens on one of those servers.
there is no fault tolerance if the deployment goes wrong.
in terms of like putting an instance in service.
those those tears and customers can't make purchases. their customers can't make online bookings.
there's no appointments being served you can't run transactions to detail.
so what caused huge huge friction right?
what were the managed services you were using in combination with the ec2 instance?
so a really good decision at the start of the guys moving to cloud.
was making a big bet on Amazon in terms of utilizing them for ODS ec2 caching.
there was no deployments DAC or there was no deployment infrastructure is code.
it was all I guess manually done through Amazon console.
which is something me later address with you know chat about.
but it was all heavily reliant on Amazon.
mm-hmm.
and you had mentioned that you were relying on one person to do deployment.
was was that still the case at this time?
yeah so open till I guess 2000 2014.
it was all reliant on one guy who who literally had to bring his laptop on holidays.
when I'm a tether from cafes if it something went down to deploy new code.
he was stealing got here we didn't had to do it so it was a huge pain point loss factor. mm-hmm.
so it sounds like in terms of how the team was split up.
there was basically you have people working on development.
and you have a single person in the sort of ops role?
yeah and essentially when when this kind of thing happens.
you the people who write the code don't ship it.
you get all sorts of problems in terms of dependencies and tangles.
and and you know just just knowledge knowledge silos.
and also you because the guys were working a kind of in their own verticals.
different areas as a product.
there was no consistency consistency in terms of the engineering values.
how they were working practices procedures you know deployments that sort of stuff.
it was all it was all very isolated.
so um people did their own talk their own thing.
so you could imagine for say trying to hire someone new would be quite hard.
because of them you know for someone to come in very very different.
depending on which engineer you talk to that makes sense yeah.
was was this a locally located team or was this a remote team?
yeah so and most of the guys were actually in Dublin.
and one or two people travelled a little bit worked remotely. and a couple of people did actually move abroad.
so it was predominantly based in Dublin but um some people travel a bit.
in terms of processes for someone knowing how to deploy or how to work on a feature.
it was mostly tribal knowledge it's more just trying to piece together a story.
from talking to different people is that correct? precisely.
so you had no consistency in languages or frameworks.
except I would say that that monolith that that initial part of the platform.
was extremely consistent in terms of the patterns used.
did the I guess the way it communicated with database.
and you know how the API was built was extremely strong.
and is is the heart of still is the heart of the organization.
so say for example there was there's a lot of really good sa integration and unit tests there.
but they got abandoned for a little while.
I mean we had to bring them back back to life to to enable us to start moving faster again.
and to give us a lot more confidence in our releases.
mmm.
so it sounds like maybe the initial version and the first year or so had a pretty solid foundation.
but then as I'm not sure if it was the team that grew or just the the rate of features.
would you say that kind of?
I would say it was a combination of the the growth of the company.
in terms of the number of customers on it.
and the focus on delivering features focusing on feature development.
rather than thinking about scalability.
and being extremely aware of. mmm.
how fast were you gaining customers at that time was this a steady increase or large spikes?
Oh your job you're copying 30 percent annually so okay.
I'm really really low chair might as well so.
what would you feel was the turning point.
where it felt like your software had or your business had to fundamentally change.
due to the number of customers you had?
so it was essentially those issues around stability and cost.
we're we're unsustainable for the business.
customers complaining our staff not being able to to do their job.
so you know part of forest core values and mission is to help the salon owner grow their business.
and use use the tools that we provide to do that.
and if people are firefighting and not being able to support our customers.
to being able to send help them send really great marketing campaigns to boost the revenue.
if we're not doing that and we're we're firefighting the company would have been pointless.
so we weren't feeling our mission by coping with outages and panicking all the time.
the costs again were unsustainable.
and you know the team you know was just I guess uncomfortable with this the state we're in.
so the turning point would have been I would say in like 2014. when we essentially hired in some people.
who have more boring experience in I would say high scalability systems.
and people who who cared a little bit more about quality and best practices.
so when you hire tree for people like that.
you kind of you bring in a different way of thinking.
you kind of you hire hired these different values.
you know when you when you try to to talk to a team and try and get these things out.
they're normally quite organic both if you bring people in from maybe a similar cut.
they're all from you know a different industry but similar experience.
you kind of get that for free that's what forest did.
so basically in 2014 and since now we've we've invested heavily in hiring.
and hiring the the right people in terms of how they operate. and in terms of headache Inc.
but also bringing that back to our values and and what we tried to do do.
you think that bringing in you know new new people new talent.
is really one of the largest factors that allowed you to make such large changes.
to change your culture and change your way of thinking?
the other thing would be I would say the trust that Ronin Co and the leadership team.
virus has and their openness to change.
I think that a lot of our organizations would be quite scared of this type of change.
in terms of heavily investing in the product to make it better.
just like from experience and talking to the people you know.
it would have been very easy to to not invest you know and just leave the software taking along with bugs. and handling the downtime.
but it was it was about the organization and their value their values around really.
helping helping the salon owners and and not spending that time firefighting.
so it sounds like within two years or so of launch was when you decided to make this change?
yeah so and you know it's not an easy one to make.
because you know it's really hard to find talent.
and we we were looking to really get some great people in.
and it wasn't about making radical change at the start you know it started from foundations.
so it was things like you know.
let's get a continuous integration server going here guys.
and you know that's let's bring all about.
let's bring back all the broken tests and make sure they're running.
so that we can have a bit more confidence of what we share we.
you know introduce code review code reviews and pull requests back into things.
and a bit more collaboration and getting rid of those pockets of knowledge.
when you no reliance on individuals.
I do want to go more into those a little bit later.
okay but before that when you were having performance issues or having outages.
before all these changes how were you finding out?
was it being reported by users or did you have any kind of process you know to notify you?
so the quite common thing was basically the phones would would light up.
there was very very little transparency of what was going on the system.
we got to a stage where we actually installed a physical red button.
on support' floor which texted everyone in the engineering team. oh wow.
okay one of the things that we often hear is when a system has issues like this.
it's difficult to free up people to fix the underlying problems.
due to the time investment required.
and as you mentioned all the fire fighting going on how did you overcome this issue?
so I guess you know the beforehand it was it was a matter of.
you know restart the server let's keep going with her features.
but it was really about stopping to think about um.
you know what really happened here.
and you know maybe let's write down an incident report and got her some data about what.
what actually happened under the hood.
and a few things you know a few questions key questions could be raised from that.
you know like what are we gonna do to stop this from happening again.
why didn't we know about it before for the customers.
and you know what were the steps we made to reproduce and actually fix this issue.
and what are the actions that are gonna happen.
and how are we gonna track that those actions do happen after after the issue.
let me see if I understand this correctly.
you you actually did build sort of a process.
when you would have incidents to figure out okay that was the first.
but I would say yeah so let's figure out what happened and how.
and it was just about gathering data and get and about what was.
what was really going on so let us identifies you know common things that happens.
that maybe usually we were just you know restart server and forget.
but or failover database and freak and you know everything's not normal in the cabarrus.
but as we started gathering that data we started to see common problems.
so maybe you know our deployment process isn't good enough.
and it's it's error-prone or this specific message broker isn't fault tolerant.
or the III ops and the database are too high at this time.
due to these queries happening but after we got that data we you know.
and we started really digging deep into the system.
we realized that this isn't something that you could just take two days in your sprint to start to fix and code.
just coming back to your question on finding that time to fix things.
we kind of had to make a tough call when we looked at everything to say.
you know let's stop feature work and let's stop craft work and let's fix this properly.
okay yeah so so basically you got more information on on why you were having these problems.
why you were having downtime or performance issues.
and started to build kind of a picture of and and realized that.
oh this is this is actually a very large problem.
and then has a company you made the decision that.
okay we're gonna stop feature development.
to make sure we have enough resources to really tackle this problem.
precisely and from the product side of things you know this was a big big driving factor.
and you know we wanted to build all these amazing features to help salons to grow.
oh boy we just couldn't actually deliver on them.
we couldn't have any predictability on when we delivered them.
because those are that firefighting and you know cuz we were sidetracked so much.
there was no confidence in release cycle and stability or what we could actually deliver.
so yeah it was it was a pretty hard decision for us to make in terms of business.
because we hadn't had a lot of deliverables and commitments to customers.
and to you know to our sales team.
so we we had to had to make that call.
you were mentioning earlier about how you started to bring in a continuous integration process.
before you had done that you also mentioned that there were tests in the system initially.
but then the tests kind of went away could you kind of elaborate on what you meant by that?
yeah so as I said like the kind of the core system was built with a lot of integrity.
and a lot of pretty good patterns.
for example a lot of integration tests are running against the api's were written.
and maybe where were written against a specific feature.
but they were never ran as a full suite.
so what would happen was there be maybe one or two flaky ones and they you know.
because there was no continuous integration server.
it was it was easy enough for a developer to run you know specific tests.
for that functionality that they were we're building.
but because there was the CI wasn't there there was no full suite ran.
so when when it came time to actually do that we realized you know since you know 70%.
of them are broken so they they were building cus as they developed.
and they were maybe not running those as the Support Committee right?
okay okay yeah and so adding the continuous integration process.
having some kind of build process really forced people to pay attention. to whether those tests were working or not.
mm-hmm exactly.
and just as a step on from that was you know a huge delay in getting stuff to test.
because because we relied on that one guy to build stuff.
and actually he that was you know done from a you know a little Linux box.
and the engineering floor and which was quite temperamental you'd be quite delayed.
and actually even just getting stuff into people's hands.
and it's kind of what the core of software developer rice you know getting.
getting what you build into people's hands and we just couldn't do it.
mmm.
just because the the process of actually doing a build and a deployment was so difficult? yeah exactly.
when you added the continuous integration process.
where there are other benefits that you maybe didn't expect. when you started bringing the?
so um I guess I mentioned the deployments is a big one.
I think the people started to see real benefit in terms of their workflow.
I guess along with the continuous integration was more more discipline in terms of how we worked.
so a disguise server introduced a better workflow for us.
and it helped us see real clarity in terms of the quality the system.
where we're had coverage where it didn't.
and it also helped us break up the the system a little bit.
so I mentioned majestic monolith.
so it was actually when we went to look at it.
there was five application servers sitting in one repo at the CI server.
and some crafty engineering helped us fit that up quite well.
to break at the repo into multiple application servers. hmm.
so so actually bringing in the continuous integration.
actually encouraged you to re-architect your application and in certain ways.
and break it down into smaller pieces exactly?
and really it was all about confidence. and being able to test and then know that we weren't progressing.
what do you think people saw in terms of the pain or the challenges.
from that sort of monolith set up that you think sort of inspired them to break it up?
the big one was a bug fix in one small a of the system.
meant the whole stack had to be redeployed which took errors and errors. mmm.
the other thing would have been the the speed of development.
in terms of navigating around a pretty large code base.
and the slowness of the test suite to Rome which was around 35 minutes.
when we when we started and got them all green.
the pain of running the tests and having it possible to break so many things with just one change.
maybe encourage people to just shrink things down.
so they wouldn't have to think so much about the whole picture all the time exactly?
we started to see you know a small fix or a small feature.
breaking something completely non-related.
typical example would have been due to HTTP connection configuration on a client.
breaking completely on your own related areas of the system. mmm.
okay one thing I'd like to talk about next is the monitoring.
you mentioned earlier that it was really just phone calls would come into support.
and you even had the big red button you could press.
what did you do to add monitoring to your application?
it was pretty important to mention that you know.
we talked about making a decision to stop to downhills and start fixing stuff.
so that's that's when we started you know looking at the monitoring and everything else.
like continuous integration bring back tests.
but a kind of a key point of of this evolutionary project was was the monitoring.
and so we did a few things so we upgraded our systems to be using New Relic.
to help us find errors and it was there for them.
it wasn't being utilized in a good enough way so he used the APM there.
we looked at their watch Amiri is Claira watch metrics to help us watch traffic. to help us see slow transactions.
log entries helped us a lot in terms of spotting anomalies in the logs.
Pingdom was actually a really surprising and good addition to monitoring.
and it simply just just calls any health check endpoint you want.
and it has some some nice slack and messaging integration knows that was great for us.
so it's helped us a lot so we did a couple of other things.
like some small intent tests that would give us a kind of a heartbeat. to how the system was running.
and they were also gave us the kind of confidence.
that we would know about an issue before a customer.
I'm being able to allow us to get rid of that red button.
all of these are managed services that that you either send logs to.
or check health endpoints on your system.
did you configure them somehow to text your team or send messages to your team.
when certain conditions were met?
or so we we started with just like a simple slack channel.
that would would send us any kind of DevOps related issues into into there.
and that that's kind of what helped us to change the culture a little bit.
in terms of being more aware of the EDM structure and the operations.
and Pingdom was great for said setting up.
a team with people who who would get notifications for various parts of the system.
and are glad watch alarms.
we set up a little lambda function that would just forward on than any critical messages to text us.
and before this you said it was basically just user calls.
and now you were actually shifting to kind of proactively identifying the problems.
yeah yeah exactly.
there was some small reef small alerts there but nothing as comprehensive as this.
we actually we changed some of the applications we introduced health endpoints all of them.
so they report on their ability to connect to message broker.
their ability to connect to a database.
any dependencies that they actually needed we would actually check as part of pinging that endpoint.
so if you hit any of our servers we any new or older ones.
they would all have like forward slash health end point to note.
give you back a Jason structure and give us a good insight into how healthy that component was. and if there was a problem.
and you were trying to debug issues were you mostly able to log into these third-party services.
like log entries or new relic to actually track down the problem?
yeah so again those services give us that information.
but it would always come back to you know being it.
if you needed to get into a server.
and a big thing which we'll talk about is docker.
we don't have SSH access into those servers.
so we rely on those turd parties to give us that information.
but in the past maybe we would have had to get in and you know.
look at the processes and take dumps.
but with log entries and New Relic we were able to do that stuff without needing to. mmm.
so previously you might have someone actually ssh into the individual boxes.
and look at log files and things like that exactly?
so quite easy when you've got one server.
both as we'll discuss when you've got many small containers and extremely complicated.
mm-hmm.
next I'd like to talk about since you mentioned docker.
how did you make the decision to move to docker?
so it was something our CTO was really aware of.
and he he really wanted us to explore this.
the big benefits for us was that shift and mindset.
of one guy not being responsible for deployments.
but us actually developing and using docker in our day-to-day workflow.
and the cost implications as well.
that the fact that we could instead of having that say 8 X large.
we could have run in one application server we could have twelve containers.
running on much smaller containers running on an ec2 instances.
so it was that idea of being able to to maximize CPU and memory.
what was a huge huge benefit for us that we saw. mmm.
so the the primary driver was was almost your AWS bill or your big time yeah.
ok ok.
portable applications that you know had much less maintenance.
we didn't have to go in and worry about because we had a.
I guess a we mentioned this earlier like these kind of siloed tech stocks.
we didn't need to worry about a ruby environment or PHP environment or Java JPM install.
it was just in the container and that it was a big an important thing for us to do.
it was really kind of well Tony but our CTO at the time.
so you mentioned like ruby containers and jaebeum's and things like that.
does your application actually have a bunch of different frameworks and a bunch of different languages?
yeah so as we split out the that model it we also.
I guess started building smaller domain-specific micro it's a kind of services.
responsible for four areas of the system.
our online booking stack so if you go to any of our customers you know.
you can book and their point-of-sale system in the salon.
but you can also book on your phone.
and we have a custom domain for every one of those.
so it's like farce com4 slash book for it slash foundation hair.
if you click on that you're going to be brought to the online booking stack.
which is a rails app actually on an ember and bjs front dent.
so the system as we started spilling it apart became more and more distributed.
and docker was great for us in terms of consistency and that portability.
particularly around different tech stocks.
migrating to docker made it easier for you to both develop and to deploy.
using a bunch of different tech stocks exactly?
when running through your CI pipeline.
would you configure it to create an image that you would put into a private registry.
such as Amazon's elastic container registry?
yeah so we make the mistake of building hosting our own registry at the start.
we quickly realized the pain and that around tree form once in.
where I'm actually at the same time as I was on released the EC or.
so I guess the main reason we did that ourselves was because we were early adopters.
and we you pay paid a little tax on that.
but we did we moved to ECR.
so our typical application kind of pipeline is build unit tests.
maybe integration acceptance tests build a container.
then some of those applications they run acceptance tests against a container running on the CI server. push push to the registry.
and after it's pushed to the registry then we would configure deployment and trigger it off.
do you have a manual process where somebody watches the pipeline go through.
and you make the call to push or not or is it a automated process? automated.
so we built a small kind of deployment framework again.
because we were early adopters of Amazon's ECS their container service.
so we built a small deployment stack.
which which allowed us to to essentially configure new services and ECS.
and deploy new versions of our application through the CI to our VCS clusters.
so it was all automated.
were using an infrastructure as code solutions such as cloud formation?
yeah so when we were in looking back at the problems in the old good old days.
you know we seen that one was you know.
things were just configured on the AWS console.
and we knew we needed infrastructure as code.
and we needed repeatability and the ability to recreate stuff.
so we reused formation and essentially what what very simple thing. very similar to terraform.
and we do use terraform for for some of our managing arresting clusters and some other things.
okay so you may be initially moved from having someone manually going in.
and creating virtual machines to more of a infrastructure as code approach exactly? yeah.
you you had mentioned that one of the primary drivers of using docker was performance.
did you start creating performance metrics so that you knew how much progress you were making. in that front?
yeah so essentially that the effort to kind of make our infrastructure more reliable.
it's it was a set as kind of a set of steps to get there.
and we started with API level testing to make sure that anything we changed under the hood.
it didn't break the intent functionality.
and we also wrote a bunch of performance tests.
particularly around pulling down appointments creating appointments.
and sending large large volumes of messages.
we we knew we couldn't have any regressions there.
so we use gatling to do those performance tests.
I mean we would run that from continuous integration server.
and we do various types of soak testing to make sure we weren't taking any steps backwards.
so each time you would do a deployment you would run performance tests.
to ensure that you weren't getting slower.
or you weren't having any problems from the new deployment?
yeah I would say though that like this kind of effort week we call the project Darwin internally.
this effort to kind of it had a few goals.
but it was all about you know becoming fault-tolerance being more scalable.
reducing Amazon costs and during project are when we we didn't just move our twelve.
fifteen hundred Cylons we didn't just drop them and move them to docker. it was so many changes under the hood.
these performance sets were key to to giving us a pulse on how we were doing.
but um I guess when we were done with project Aaron.
and every everything was on docker and and everyone was much much happier.
and we just we run those performance tests ad hoc.
and as as part of some release pipelines. mmm.
okay so initially you were undergoing a lot of big changes.
and that was where it was really important to check the performance metrics with with every build exactly?
what were some of the the big challenges because you mentioned you were changing a lot of things.
what were some of the big challenges moving your existing architecture to docker into ECS?
there was a couple the biggest there's two huge ones.
so one was state getting state out of those big servers was extremely hard.
we needed to remove the level 2 cache.
because we need because we needed to turn that one server into smaller low balance containers.
we needed to remove the state.
because we didn't want somebody in one turn computer terminal fetching their appointments.
and then on their first go mobile app looking at different data.
so we had to get rid of state.
and the challenge there was that MySQL performance just wasn't good enough for us.
so we actually had to look really hard at migrating at Amazon Aurora which is what we did.
again coming back to cost Aurora is much more cost-effective.
in terms of the system before hand was provisioned for peak load.
so we would have provisioned I ops for Friday afternoon.
the busiest time that the salon was using the system.
and we were paying that for the same amount on a Sunday night.
compared to Aurora where you're paying for I ops.
and the additional benefits of performance around how Amazon rebuilt the storage engine there.
so that's the caching side of things the other big big challenge was the VP C.
so we needed to get all of our applications into a VP c2.
to be able to use the the latest instance types on Amazon.
and also the fur application be able to talk security to Aurora database.
so those two are definitely the biggest challenges with the my sequel set up.
it sounded like you had to pay for your peak usage.
whereas with Aurora it automatically scales up and down is that correct?
no you're actually charged per read and write.
so that would be the big yellow eyes see per read and write.
okay yeah so it's just per operations.
so you don't actually think about what your needs are gonna be.
it kind of just charges you based on how it's used.
yeah the current a really nice thing was looking back at our incident reports.
a really common issue would have been hey two databases ran out of storage.
and Rory does actually always gets its storage engine.
you mentioned removing state from your servers.
and you you mentioned removing the level two cache.
can you kind of explain sort of at a high level what that means.
to those who don't understand that part? sure.
so in the Java world when you have an ORM framework like hibernate.
essentially when you create a database the scash will store that data in its level two cache.
and what that means is that it doesn't need to hit the database for every query.
and that's the that was the solution for for forests.
as we were in that MVP slash early days but it wasn't the solution first when to become fault tolerant.
so it would be someone makes a query to an or in this case it's and it's hibernate.
and on the server's memory it would retrieve the results from there instead of from the database?
yeah exactly okay.
and that's what I was coming back to around creating an API for a list of appointments.
if you had two servers deployed wait with them using an l2 cache.
you would get different state because cache.
so did you put a different cache in place or did you remove the cache entirely?
so we removed that cache entirely.
but we did have a rest cache which is was memcache D.
and that's distributed and we use cache keys based on two diversions.
so that was distributed and worked well with multiple containers behind a load balancer.
so you remove the the cash from the individual servers.
but you do have managed memcached instance that you use?
yeah exactly and getting rid of that level two cache share performance tests told us that.
MySQL just what there wasn't performant enough whereas Aurore was much better.
handling that those types of queries some large joints it was a big big relational database.
so we we've talked about adding in continuous integration monitoring performance metrics.
Aurora docker did any of these processes require large changes to your code base?
to be honest not really it was more about plumbing things together.
a lot of orchestration from a human point of view.
so um people being aware of how all this stuff worked.
and essentially making sure that we only were on the right page.
I don't like the biggest piece of engineering and coding work.
was the deployment and infrastructure script.
so provisioning the bbc's writing the integrations with ECS that sort of thing.
but in terms of actual coding that wasn't too invasive.
I think that's actually a positive for a lot of people.
because I believe there are people who think they need to do a big rewrite.
if they have you know performance problems.
or problems keeping track of the status of their system.
but I think this is a good case study that shows you don't necessarily need to do a rewrite.
you just need to put additional processes and checks in place.
and maybe change your deployment process to kind of get the results that you want.
it's bad foundations as well.
if you have some really strong people at the start who you know paved some good roads there.
in terms of good practices like just for example.
a really good database change management set up.
some good packaging of the code really good packaging of the code.
so it was quite easy for us to slip out five services from that big monument. it's about the foundations at the start.
because it would be quite easy to to build an MVP with some people.
who who write you know tears and line PHP scripts and the product works.
and that's a different case study because you know you cut we can't fix that essentially right.
so it's because the original foundation was strong.
that you were able to undergo this sort of transformation yeah? truly yeah.
adopting all of these processes did they resolve all of the key problems. your your business faced?
when we when we look back and we see that you know all of our systems are running on docker.
we see a huge cost benefit so that problem was certainly solved.
we were able to see issues before our customers.
so we had better transparency in the system.
no longer was where we dependent on one big server went as.
and customers were no longer dependable big server.
and so it meant that we we have really good week.
and we do have really good fault tolerance on on those containers.
if one of them dies ECS will literally kill us bring up a new one.
it will also do some auto scaling first say on Monday morning.
it will maybe have eight containers running but on a Friday maybe it'll auto scale 14.
so that's been grande bag breaking for us in terms of how we work.
we went from shipping monthly to quarterly.
from between monthly and quarterly to to daily.
and something I use is a team held metric right now is our frequency of deployment.
and I'd say we're hitting about twenty five deployments a week now.
compared to the olden days is is great we always want to get better at it.
I would say that those have been really amazing things for us.
but also in terms of the team it's a lot easier for us now to hire a new engineer and bring them in.
because this consistency and also I guess we're not reliant on these pockets of knowledge anymore.
so we again around hiring it's it's a lot easier for someone to come into the system. and and know how things work.
and I think in terms of hiring as well when you talk about the kind of setup.
it's it's you know you know there's some some good stuff happening there.
it sounds like you have a better picture in terms of monitoring the system.
you brought your costs down significantly the deployment process is much easier.
the existence of the containers and ECS is kind of serving the purpose.
of where people used to have to monitor the individual servers and bring them up themselves.
but now you sort of outsource that to Amazon to take care of.
does that sound is that all sound correct?
yes and I find it interesting to that you had mentioned.
that improving all of your processes actually made it easier to bring new people in.
and that's because you were saying things are now more clearly defined in terms of what to do.
rather than all of this information kind of being tribal in a sense?
yeah like a typical example will be like hey let's redeploy this bug-fix.
and say previously you know it might be a Capistrano deploy.
or you know oh you need to get SSH keys to this thing.
and you need to log in here and you need to build this code on this local machine.
and try and ship it off and that just all goes away.
particularly with docker and that that continuous integration pipeline.
is just it sense a really good set of standards.
and things that people should find quite you know easy and repeatable.
and so now in terms of deployment you can use something like cloud formation.
and you have the continuous integration process that can deploy your software.
without somebody having to know specifically about how that part works exactly?
so I would say if we wanted to create like a new service.
responsible for some new new functionality in forest spring boot application.
a job application they can simply provide a docker file.
and get that deployed to dead of staging or production we.
I would say ten lines of yam all configuration.
so you could go from initial setup of project to production in a day if you wanted to.
just zero friction there and say. mm-hmm.
it really makes the onboarding a lot easier than.
do you think your team waited too long to change their processes.
or do you think these changes came at just the right time?
I would say if we waited any longer it could have been detrimental to to.
I guess the health of the business.
I think that the guys did a great job in terms of getting us to a certain point.
but we would have risk technical decay I would say.
and what kind of really hurt hiring that their organization.
if I had have gone any further.
I would say it was it was a lot of work to do this.
and it could have been easier if if we had have paid more attention to a technical debt.
and making the right decisions earlier on.
so maybe saying no to that customer who wants a spoke piece of functionality.
what you have to do what you have to do so.
you would say maybe identifying earlier on just how much the current processes were causing you problems.
if you had identified that earlier you think you might have made the decision.
to try and make these changes at an earlier time?
yes so the guys earlier we're making really good decisions.
but maybe they didn't have the experience for her.
you know higher scale at the scalability solutions and systems.
so it's it's about hiring the right people at different stages of where the product is evolving.
I would say given what you've gone through with the migration at forest.
what advice would you give to someone building a new process.
what what can they do to keep ahead of either technical dead.
or any of the other issues you faced?
I think it's about how it's actually a people and cultural thing.
along with tech decisions so everybody needs to be really aligned in terms of those decisions.
that they're making rather than letting people go on an individual basis.
I think there needs to be good leadership in terms of getting a group of people thinking the same way.
I reckon that technical currency is is extremely important.
and as your system grows you need to be able to look look back and identify areas of pain.
and buy pain I mean you know speed of deployment.
speed of an development and ability to adapt and change your software.
so if you notice that a feature that used to maybe take a week is now taking two weeks.
you know you probably need to take a really hard look at that area of the system.
and figure it could it be simplified I'm white.
why is it taking too long basically identifying exactly where your pain points are.
so that you can really focus your efforts.
and have an idea of what you're really going for?
yeah you need to build an environment of trust.
and I will also say that you need to be able to to be able to become a confident.
and okay with failure in terms of taking risks sometimes.
and saying no to features and customers to be able to push back on leadership.
and make sure that you're really evolving the system the right way. and not just becoming a feature Factory.
yeah it's always gonna be a kind of balance on you know.
how much can you pull back but still stay competitive in whatever space you're in.
yeah so what we're doing right now based on those lessons.
is we tried to do like a six to eight week burst of work.
and we would always try and take a week or two wiggle room between that and starting something new.
to look back at what we just built and we're happy with it.
but also look at our our technical backlog. and see if there's anything there that's really paying us.
and just even for example this week we we noticed an issue.
with a lot of bills failing on our CI.
because of how how it was set up to push docker images.
so occasionally they would fail and that was actually a real pain point for us.
just over the last couple of months.
because maybe a deployment which Toshio take 20 minutes was taking 40.
because you'd have to retry ger it.
so that's just like that's an example of us looking at what what was high value.
and making sure we just fix it before we start something new.
so making sure that you don't kind of end up in the same situation.
where you started where these technical issues sort of build without people noticing them.
instead kind of in shorter iterations doing sort of a sanity check.
and making sure like everything is working and we're all going in the right direction? yeah it's about the team and I mentioned before.
it's about you know the leadership and a group of people together talking through common issues.
and you know maybe meet meet every two three weeks talk about some key metrics in the system.
why is it this - hi why is this too low?
you know you can truly kind of treat your peers.
you can really see the pain points and they'll more than likely tell you them.
when you look back at all the different technologies and processes you adopted.
did you feel that any of them had too much overhead for someone starting out?
what was your experience in general?
so some people just didn't like doing code reviews.
some people just really just felt that they could just push push what they needed.
and that it was almost a judgment on them in terms of the code review process.
which it totally wasn't I would say.
some people found Jenkins and continues integration a bit you know what's the point.
so we had we had some you know some pain points there.
but as we got to docker as people seen the benefits of these things.
you know less bugs going into production lest things breaking. people being able to go home nice and early in the evening.
and not be woke up in the middle of night with a you know an outage call.
those are the world that the benefits.
and that's reaping the rewards of thinking like this.
your team was bringing on a bunch of new things at once.
what was your process for adopting all these new things without overwhelming your team?
so it was starting at the foundation.
so the continuous integration the code reviews were were incrementally brought in.
then we we had regular team meetings to discuss pros and cons.
and it was really important for people to import on those things.
rather than to just it implement them they would have failed.
if we had have done it like that it took time I know it still.
I would say we're still not in perfect world.
but it's about group group consensus and and making sure that.
everyone everyone's bought in to to what we're trying to achieve. mmm.
so basically getting everyone in the same room.
and making sure they understand what exactly the goal is.
and everyone's on the same page?
yes so we tried to make a big effort particularly for people who are working remotely.
to get them all in the same room once a quarter.
we talked about our challenges talked about our goals talked about our values.
and make sure we're all on the same page and sometimes we tweak them.
and you know that's how we feel it's best to do it.
great finally I want to talk about what's next for for Forrest.
what are the remaining pain points you have now and and what do you plan on tackling next?
so right now we're on fortes and Cylons on our platform.
we're really happy with the state of the infrastructure to get us to maybe eight ten thousand Cylons.
but we need to be really conscious of the company's growth and our goals.
so we need to make sure that we can scale in a much bigger level.
and we also need to make sure that our customers aren't affected by groped.
we're looking at server lists for any kind of newer pieces of the product.
to see if they can help us reduce costs even more.
and and help us stay stay agile in terms of our infrastructure and how we roll out.
a couple years ago when we launched into the USA.
we noticed we it doubled our overhead in terms of infrastructure operations and deployment.
and as we grow in the u.s.
we we need to be really conscious of not making it any I guess mistakes from the past.
so you're mostly looking forward to additional scaling challenges.
and possibly addressing those with survey lists or some other type of technology?
yeah so one area in particular will be our SMS sending.
so that's kind of a plan for the next six to eight months.
would be to make sure that we can continue to scale at the growth rate of SMS.
and email sending which is is huge in the platform.
mmm.
you said so far you've been experiencing 30% growth year over year.
and you said when you moved to the u.s. you actually doubled your customer base?
I'd say we doubled our overhead in terms of infrastructure mounting deployments.
we we're still very early stage in the US and that's our big focus for the moment.
but as we grow there we we need to be.
I guess more operationally aware of how it's I was going over there.
there's a much bigger market to kind of cap it off. how how can people follow you on the Internet?
sure so you can grab me on Twitter John will Dornan jo hn w al Doran.
and if you ever want to reach out to me and talk to about any of this type of sulphides.
I'd love to to meet up with you so feel free to reach out.
all right John thank you so much for coming on the show.
thanks so much for having me.
this is Jeremy Jung for software engineering radio thank you for listening.
thanks for listening to se radio.
an educational program brought to you by Triple E software magazine.
for more about the podcast including other episodes visit our website at SE - radio net.
to provide feedback you can comment on each episode on the website.
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter.
or through our slack channel at SC radio.com.
you can also email us at team at SC - radio net.
this and all other episodes of se Radio is licensed under Creative Commons license 2.5. thanks for listening.